<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the consecration of a chappel in the house of John Collins, Esq., of Chute in Wiltshire, performed by the Right Reverend Father in in [sic] God Seth, Lord Bishop of Sarum, on the 25th of September, 1673 by Joseph Kelsey ...</title>
            <author>Kelsey, Joseph, d. 1710.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47212</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K249</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2647</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13663415</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13663415</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101138</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47212)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101138)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 792:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the consecration of a chappel in the house of John Collins, Esq., of Chute in Wiltshire, performed by the Right Reverend Father in in [sic] God Seth, Lord Bishop of Sarum, on the 25th of September, 1673 by Joseph Kelsey ...</title>
                  <author>Kelsey, Joseph, d. 1710.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Edwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Kings, 1st, IX, 3 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101138:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101138:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED at the Conſecration OF A CHAPPEL In the HOUSE of <hi>JOHN COLLINS,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Of <hi>CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TE</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Performed by the Right Reverend Father in in God <hi>SETH,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Sarum,</hi> on the 25th of <hi>September,</hi> 1673.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOSEPH KELSEY,</hi> B. D. Rector of <hi>Newton-Tony</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Autholog. in Dedicat. Templi Reſurrect. Dom.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonathan Edwin,</hi> at the three Roſes in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet,</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:101138:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101138:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND Father in God SETH Lord Biſhop of <hi>SAR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe occaſion of this Sermon, which but rarely happen's, having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded me to the publiſhing of it; The extraordinary favours which I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly received from your Lordſhip, will, I hope, excuſe the prefixing ſo great a Name to ſo inconſiderable a Paper. I humbly beg, that it may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted
<pb facs="tcp:101138:3"/>as a teſtimony of my Sincere acknowledgments and that the innocent Deſign hereof may not be denyed the Protection of ſo Revered a Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips in all duty, moſt Obedient Servant. JOSEPH KELSEY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101138:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at the CONSECRATION of a Chappel in the Houſe of <hi>JOHN COLLINS,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Kings 9.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And the Lord ſaid unto him, I have heard thy Prayer, and thy Supplication, which thou haſt made before me. I have hallowed this Houſe that thou haſt built, to put my Name there for ever, and mine eyes and mine heart ſhall be there perpetually.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe Words are the beginning of that Anſwer, which God gave to <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Prayer, at the Dedication of the Temple. The Devotion of which Service, (ſet down in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Chapter) equal to the Magnificence of the building, worthy (if any thing can be ſo) of that Majeſty, whoſe acceptance they ſupplicated, doth both invite and juſtifie, and is no leſs the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, than an Example to this dayes ſolemnity. For though a Promiſe of ſo much grace and favour may ſeem proportionate to nothing, but the glory of <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple, and the Priviledges here grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101138:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>too big for a private Chappel, yet ſince immen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity can be no more contained in one, than in the other, and the intentions of the Founders (which God alwayes reſpects) may be equally full of Piety and Religion: He whoſe Glory filled that Houſe, may alſo fill a leſſer Oratory; and He, who bids us enter into our Cloſets, doth thereby hallow the place; and ſuppoſe a preſence attentive to every Religious performance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon</hi> likewiſe underſtood very well, both as a Philoſopher, and a Divine, by Reaſon, as by Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, the infinite nature of God and His Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſence; that the Heaven of Heavens could not contain him, much leſs the Houſe which he had built. He intended not to impriſon the Godhead, in a place of thirty Cubits high, or to nail the Divinity (as the Heathens did the Goddeſs of Victory) to the Walls of His Temple: he forgot not, that a clean Heart, and a purified Soul, were the habitations which God loved; and ſincere Obedience, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice wherein He delighted; he foreſee all thoſe weak reaſonings, which have ſince heen uſed to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage that Piety in the World (which wants much rather to be inflamed) and to accuſe the moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious deſignes of Idolatry and Superſtition. He ſee them (I ſay) and did confute them: and ſo did God himſelf. For it came to paſs, when <hi>Solomon</hi> had finiſhed the Houſe of the Lord, the Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared unto him and ſaid, <hi>I have heard thy Prayer, and thy Supplication which thou haſt made</hi> &amp;c. From which words we will conſider,
<list>
                  <item>1. The meaning of to Hallow or Sanctifie.</item>
                  <item>2. The Dedication of Places to Gods Worſhip.</item>
                  <item>3. The Effects of it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101138:4"/>There is a twofold Holineſs in Scripture, <hi>Original</hi> and Eſſential in God; and that which is <hi>derived,</hi> in things that have relation to Him. The firſt doth neceſſarily belong to God, as He is the moſt perfect Being, in whom all Excellencies do poſſeſs infinite perfection. So that the firſt notion of Holineſs in Him is a Supereminent Greatneſs in all His Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of Wiſdom, Power, and Goodneſs. He is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten called the <hi>Holy One of Iſrael,</hi> the <hi>Excellency of Jacob.</hi> There is none holy as the Lord; none com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to Him in the Greatneſs of all His Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. Hence the Name of God is joyned to words to expreſs their Greatneſs. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (<hi>Gen.</hi> 1.)<note place="margin">Vide R. Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monem Melech. in locum.</note> which we tranſlate <hi>The Spirit of God,</hi> the Jewes expound a great and ſtrong wind moving upon the face of the waters, <hi>Nineveh</hi> was a great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> very great. So the Cedars of God, and the Mountains of God. So alſo amongſt the Greeks <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is expounded by the Scholiaſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, every way great and full of Majeſty. He that hath arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to any extraordinary attainment of Power, Learning, or Piety hath merited to be called <hi>Vir Magnus,</hi> and all the Severity of Stoical virtues did make up that <hi>Magnitudo animi</hi> of which <hi>Cato</hi> loved ſo often to diſpute. But Holineſs in created Beings is founded in that relation they have to God, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated or ſeparated to His peculiar uſe and ſervice. The Sabbath is called a holy day, —<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Judaea</hi> a holy Land, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a holy City. —<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites a holy People, as God himſelf ſpeaks, <hi>I have ſeparated you from other people, that you ſhould be mine, and ye ſhall be a holy People unto me.</hi> And
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101138:5"/>in other places, peculiar and proper are the ſame with Holy: Nor are thoſe great Titles, wherewith the Apoſtle hath dignified the Churches, to which he writes (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) of any other ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, than that they (as of old the <hi>Jews</hi>) had entertained the Profeſſion of a Religion, diſtinct from others of the World, and of a far more Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelation; whereby they might be excited to the Acquiſition of thoſe Excellencies, which in the Object of their Worſhip they did adore; and thoſe names (of an as extended meaning, as that of Chriſtians) ſhew rather what they ought to be, than aſſure us what they were; for amongſt thoſe Saints were found ſtrange Immortalities, altogether contradictory to the Sacredneſs of their Vocation. So fallacious is it, from the moſt ſpecious pretences to infer a Real Sanctity: becauſe Hypocriſie is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Ancient Crime; and that Accuſation hath always been too juſt,<note place="margin">Inſtit, Proemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m.</note> which <hi>Quintilian</hi> charged upon the Philoſophers of his Age, <hi>Non enim virtute &amp; ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diis, ut haberentur Philoſophi labor abant, ſed vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp; triſtitiam, &amp; diſſentientem à caeteris habitum peſſamis moribus praetendebant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To Hallow therefore, or to Sanctifie, is to treat any thing, or to behave our ſelves towards it, as the Nature of its Holineſs ſhall require. We then hallow the Name of God, when with the deepeſt ſenſe we acknowledge his Greatneſs, fear his Power, love his Goodneſs, truſt his Faithfulneſs, devoutly admire and imitate every of his Excellencles, when all our thoughts, words, and actions, are ſtill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed moſt becoming of his Majeſty; nor in them any thing unworthy of ſo incomparable a Being (whoſe, both as Creatures and Chriſtians, we are)
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101138:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>is to be found. The contrary to this, is to prophanc and pollute his Holy Name; not giving that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which is due unto it, either by Atheiſm, which doth not only deny Honour, but ſuperadds Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; or Polytheiſm, dividing and making com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon that Religious Worſhip, which the notion of one God challenges as incommunicable and proper to it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Perſons are then hallowed, when being ſeparated from the more common imployments of the World, and dedicated to the peculiar Service of God in managing the Offices of Religion, they enjoy that honour and reſpect which is due to the Agents of ſo great a Maſter: And ſo the Prieſthood hath been honoured in all Ages, in all Religions; their Perſons eſteemed Sacred as their Office, and received with all the Differences, which are wont to make a Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation Glorious and Reſplendent: and if to the great attainments of the Age wherein we live, the want of this may be reckoned a ſtrong Exception, (the contempt of the Clergy being become the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Books and Diſcourſes) in vain ſhall we trouble our ſelves in ſearching out other Reaſons of that Incivility, which muſt be ultimately reſolved into the decay of Reverence to Religion, and of Loyalty to God himſelf. Where this is not, what Learning, Wiſdom, or Piety can oblige? or what could have defended him whom — <hi>Nec</hi> Apollinis <hi>infula texit?</hi> In the mean while, we cannot but juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wonder, that he who all along pretends to have laid the Foundations of his Commonwealth in the obſervation of Humane Nature, the Humours, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, and Practiſes of Univerſal Mankind, ſhould not remember that there never was any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101138:6"/>Time, or Place, how Barbarous ſoever, which was not Highly Civil in this; and thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves bound to reward the Procurators of their Religion with the beſt and greateſt of worldly things. So that the effect of his Politicks may be very much to ſpoil Chriſtianity, by complying with the corrupt humours of men; but ſhall never be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to introduce any other way of Religion, the Prieſthood whereof ſhall not have a conſiderable Rule and Intereſt in the World, when all he hath ſaid to the contrary ſhall be forgotten.</p>
            <p>The Sanctification which the Chriſtian Doctrine teacheth, (deveſted of thoſe adventitious niceties, whereby the diſputing humour of ſome hath much ſpoiled the ancient ſimplicity of its Nature) is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved into the two things we have diſcourſed: (1) The Dedication of our ſelves to God <hi>(viz.)</hi> in Baptiſm: (2) And the management of our ſelves according to the Holineſs of that Relation: For in Baptiſm we were admitted into the Church, incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated into that Divine Society, and made Parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of all the Priviledges of the Goſpel. Here we were taken into the Protection of the Holy Ghoſt, as the <hi>Jews</hi> ſay their Baptized Proſelite was put <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> under the Wings of the Divinity: by the aſſiſtance of which H. Spirit, the Power of Original Sin (whereinſoever it doth conſiſt) is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballanced, and our own induſtry concurring, made ineflectual; as the <hi>Jews</hi> alſo believed the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> vicious inclination was taken away by Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So that ſince the infuſion of Vertuous Habits hath but ſeldom been experienced, and brings but little reaſon, for which in theſe our days we ſhould believe it, what can be demanded more, as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101138:6"/>to our Sanctification, than to be put into poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thoſe Spiritual helps, which are always aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting our ſincere endeavours? or where can we fix the date of it, but in that Sacrament where ſuch a Right was beſtowed? Hither alſo muſt be referred Regeneration, Adoption and Juſtification, all which Bleſſings are the Acts of God, by that means which in his Church he hath ordained, by Baptiſm confirmed unto us: But whether or no we have forfeited them in our after-lives, will not be known till the Day of Judgment. For they are all Judicial Acts, and the words, with many more in our Religion, terms not only of the Jewiſh, but Roman Law; and do, in their nature, ſuppoſe a Corporation, but as diſtinct from the Temporal, as the things ſignified by them tranſcend the Graces of Princes, or the indulgences of any Imperial Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. To this I will only add, that if in Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy, Philoſophy, Anatomy, and other Sciences, that <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> is by all eſteemed beſt and neareſt truth, which doth moſt eaſily, naturally and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtently explain the appearances proper to it; then that the Church is a diſtinct Society, (though upon no other reaſons) will ſtrongly challenge our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, becauſe upon this doth depend the Nature of many Eſſential parts in Religion, the Solution of which is in vain elſewhere to be expected.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing is the Dedication of Places for Gods Worſhip; where we will enquire (1) The Antiquity of them. (2) What this Dedication doth imply as the reaſonableneſs of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It cannot be doubted that Religion is as Old as Humane Nature, the ſenſe of mans own neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties forcibly producing an acknowledgment of a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101138:7"/>more Excellent Being, upon whom he doth depend: And if Reaſon or Cogitation be the Formality of the Soul, Religion or Dependence muſt be the firſt Subject whereupon thoſe Faculties muſt be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed. But Religion (no dull or ſluggiſh, but an active and vigorous thing) will make its appearance by outward ſigns, and viſible effects; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the Infancy of the World, it ſoon put forth it ſelf in all material circumſtances: They offered Sacrifice, and at a certain time; for ſo the words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (<hi>Gen.</hi> 4.) ſignifie, a fixed period of a conſtant Revolution. That it was at a ſtated place is reaſonable, becauſe in Paradiſe there ſeems to have been one place, where more eſpecially God manifeſted his Preſence, from which <hi>Adam</hi> fled, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to be concealed. After the Flood <hi>Noah</hi> built an Altar to the Lord, and <hi>Jacob</hi> took a Stone, and ſet it for a Pillar, and called it <hi>Bethel,</hi> and endowed it with the tenth of his whole Eſtate; which the <hi>Gentiles</hi> imitating, worſhipped their Gods in the ſhape of unpoliſhed ſtones,<note place="margin">Boeharti Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gr. Sa. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and called them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Their unſetled way of living, or the imperfection of Arts, ſtinted the expreſſions of their Devotions, which in aſter-Ages let it ſelf looſe to that Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Prodigality, in the number and Magnificence of their Temples, which we read, and cannot but admire in <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Story. And this was only a true deduction from the Law of Nature; for there were Temples in the <hi>Gentile</hi> World, before either the Tabernacle of <hi>Moſes,</hi> or that of <hi>Solomon;</hi> to the building of which, neither by any Command from God, or Covenant of the Jewiſh Law, did he ſtand obliged.</p>
            <p>There was indeed a ſort of haughty and moroſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101138:7"/>Philoſophers, who alone outbraved mankind, and boaſted their own perfections, in affront to all the world beſides, who laying down, for the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their morality, That all things, out of the power of Mans own will, were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, neither good nor evils, made themſelves independent of any external cauſe, and the Spring of all their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to be in their own boſomes, upon which they grew proud, and inſolent, diſdaining to aſk the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of God himſelf. — <hi>ſtulte quid fatigas Deum? fac te felicem.</hi> It was to no purpoſe, to trouble hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for theſe things, they could beſtow upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, when they pleaſed. And as to them it ſeemed unneceſſary to pray to God; ſo they alſo thought Temples inſignificant, and no other than Monuments of mens wilful careleſsneſs in the emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of their own minds. For ſo <hi>Cato</hi> in <hi>Lucan,</hi> being adviſed to aſk counſel of <hi>Jupiter Hammons</hi> Oracle, after the death of <hi>Pompey</hi> anſwers in their uſual way of affectation.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Eſtne Dei ſedes, nifi Terra, &amp; <hi>Pontus</hi> &amp; Aër,</l>
               <l>Et Coelum, &amp; Virtus? Sùperos quid quaerimus ultra?</l>
            </q>
            <p>Jupiter <hi>eſt quodcunque vides.</hi>—<note place="margin">Plutarchus de Stoicerum Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pag.</note> and <hi>Zeno</hi> was accuſed of Atheiſm, for his Opinion, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The Omnipreſence of the Deity, and preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their own vertue, were the two Topicks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which they ſuperſeded all external ſignifications of Religion. Which method of Reaſoning is ſo contradictory to the common ſence of mankind, that it needs no other way to be refuted; beſides that the boaſtings of their ſelf-ſufficiency, how vain they were, the ſevereſt of that Sect have been forced to acknowledge. But indeed the foundation of this,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101138:8"/>and moſt their proper Opinions, was nothing but their Doctrine of Fatality, which gave life and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour to all their Singularities; which he who throughly believes, will never be able to give any other reaſon of Prayer, or any Exerciſe of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but that which <hi>Zeno</hi> gave his Servant why he beat him; a very bad one in Religion. But above all things, he will be a very Fool to put himſelf to any great trouble or expence for a Teſtimony of his Piety: he will never erect Altars, or build Temples to ſuch a God as <hi>Jupiter;</hi> who being overpowred by the more Supreme Deſtiny, when his Dear Friend was near ſlain in the War, uſes a pittiful Interjection, the invention of ſome miſerable Mortal.—
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.<note place="margin">Iliad. 4.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Univerſe, was their Supreme Deity; and Matter, and Motion, the Principles of their Divinity. And ſurely, if we conſider the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ages of Chriſtianity, who can we accuſe of that unſpeakable devaſtation of Sacred Places, but they who boaſted of their impulſes? who have introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced that barbarous ruſticity into the ſervice of God ſo much as they who have Eſpouſed the Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of the Stoicks? Was it not unſufferable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption to invite the Deity into their own Souls, by no other argument, than the prophanation of his Temples? or when they had overthrown his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, to offer him their hearts full of Sacriledge for his habitation? Into the Soul that is defiled Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom will not enter. God is ſaid to dwell in his Saints, and their Bodies are called the Temples of the H. Ghoſt. So he did of Old, and yet he loved the Gates of <hi>Sion</hi> more than all the dwellings in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem.</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101138:8"/>Vertuous qualities of the mind only make us fit to pay our Viſible Devotions, not excuſe us from them. <hi>Haec cedo, ut admoveam Templis</hi> — was the true uſe which the Satyriſt makes of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereſt honeſty: I will waſh my hands in Innocency, and ſo will I approach thy holy Altar. Some Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Writers indeed, in their Apologies for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, ſeem to ſpeak the ſenſe of this Objection. When <hi>Caecilius</hi> in <hi>Minutius</hi> asks, <hi>Cur nullas aras habent (Chriſtiani?) eur nulla ſimulacrâ?</hi> Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius anſwers, <hi>Quod enim ſimulaerum Deo fingam, cum ſit Dei homo ipſe ſimulacrum? Templum quod ei extruám, cum totus hic mundus ejus operâ fabricatus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> capere non poſſit? nonnè meliùs in noſtrâ dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candus eſt mente? in noſtro imo conſecrandus eſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctore?</hi> Some other ſuch paſſages do occur in <hi>Origen, Arnobius, Lactantius;</hi> but either they are ſpoken by way of Rhetorical compariſon, (becauſe from undoubted Authority it doth appear, that before that time the Chriſtians had not only Publick Places of Worſhip, but that they had been ſeveral times demoliſhed by the Edicts of the Emperours) or elſe they muſt be underſtood, that the Chriſtians had no ſuch Temples as the Heathens, wherein the Images of their Adored Deities were placed, the terminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Worſhip, and plain Idolatry.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of Chriſtianity, it is not reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to expect any great and ſumptuous Buildings, when the Preachers of it were of ſo poor and low condition; and their Fortunes as unſtable, as the Waters upon which they had their Habitation. What Oratories could they ſurniſh, who ſold their Ships, and all they had, to follow Chriſt? They then aſſembled in private houſes, where they had the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101138:9"/>higheſt Rooms allowed them, by the Piety of the Converted Owners, ſet apart for the ſole purpoſes of Religion: For which Charity, <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcilla, Nymphas</hi> and <hi>Philemon,</hi> ſhall be Recorded to all Generations. In the heat of Perſecutions, they met in Dens and Caves of the Earth, and ſung Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to the Great Creator in Subterraneous places, where the light of the Sun never came: in memory of which our Altars yet burn, and teſtifie our thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to God for the Liberty we enjoy. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they had their <hi>Synaxes</hi> in Woods and Groves, which then truly merited the ſtile of Sacred and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious: Sometimes in Caemeteries, and over the Tombs of them which died in the Lord; where they inflamed one anothers Zeal with the recordati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Faith, and received new Life and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage from the Aſhes of Martyrs, and hopes of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</p>
            <p>So low were the Foundations of Chriſtian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches laid, in the humility of a condition deſigned to ſuſtain the height of that glory, to which not long after, they did ariſe. For it would be too much to tell you, how theſe contemptible beginnings en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed to that proportion, as like the little Stone cut out of the Mountain, to over-top the Splendid Heatheniſme of the Nations. How they ſtruck dumb the famed Oracles of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Apollo;</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them forget their Poetry firſt, and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to eternal ſilence all their ambiguous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſes. How they overthrew the Idolatrous Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, leveled their Temples with the ground, broke in pieces the Amphitheaters, and conſecrated the Pantheons to the worſhip of the only true Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal God. How the Prieſts of the Gentiles mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101138:9"/>and with unfeigned ſorrow, early begun to ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate the Funerals of a Religion, which had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready received its mortal wound, when, the very day after the crucifixion of our Saviour,<note place="margin">Vide Voſſium de Idololatria, lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> along the Arcadian Shore it groaned, and ſighed its laſt, <hi>Great Pan is dead.</hi> The Treaſuries of the Church were no longer now ſupplyed with the mites of the poor; but filled with the Eſtates of the Rich and Honourable. One dedicated his Bathes, another his Houſe to the erection of Titles, and frequently the dying perſon commended his Soul to God, by bequeathing his Eſtate to the encouragement of Religion. So the Houſe of <hi>Pudens,</hi> a Noble Senator mentioned (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.) and of <hi>Theophilus</hi> of <hi>Antioch,</hi> St. <hi>Lukes</hi> moſt excellent Patron, were converted into Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Temples. Within an hundred years after the death of our Saviour; we read in the Dialogue aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to <hi>Lucian,</hi> called <hi>Philopatris,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſayes <hi>Critius</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Repreſenting the Aſſemblies of the Chriſtians, we paſſed through iron Gates, and brazen Threſholds, when after many winding Aſcents we came to an Houſe, whoſe Roof was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaid with Gold. Nor is the Authority of this Book made leſs, by any thing that either <hi>Blondel,</hi> in oppoſition to the Antiquity of Churches, or the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians, in favour of their Antitrinitarian Opinion, have diſputed; ſeeing it is certain (whoever was the Author) it was written (if not about the time of <hi>Nero,</hi> as ſome think, yet) in the Reign of <hi>Trajan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Marcilius adlocum.</note> whoſe conqueſts over the Parthians he plainly doth congratulate. He that conſiders the ſeveral Claſſes of Perſons, to every of which was an appointed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101138:10"/>Station in the Church, and the diſtinct degrees, through which they paſſed in the primitive diſcipline, before they were accounted perfect, muſt conclude, that not a confuſed aſſembling, but a deſigned, methodized place was onely capeable of ſo regular, and orderly proceedings.</p>
            <p>The poverty of their affairs did not diſcourage the Chriſtians, nor the rage of their enemies affright them; but they met together in hallowed places, where they prayed for the lives of their Perſecutors and did no other hurt, than what <hi>Pliny</hi> relates' in his known Epiſtle. But if at any time, either policy of State or the goodneſs of the Emperour, gave them releaſe from their afflictions, and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their religion, then could they not reſt ſatified to ſerve God, amidſt ruins and deſolations; but with ſumptuous charges, they reedified the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Churches, which, for ought they knew, the next breath of an angry Tyrant might again throw to the ground. When the Empire turned Chriſtian, then was there an Emblem of the general reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Euſeb. lib. 10. c. 2.</note> Religion ſeem to be clad in the joyes of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality: their Temples aſcended above all clouds and tempeſts, not afraid of a ſecond death. Then was there, in every Town and City, laſting monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments raiſed to that God who had at length tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the madneſs of the people, had ſpoken the word and delivered them from further fears of Stormes, and Shipwracks. Then might you have Seen the Splendor of <hi>Paulinus</hi> his Cathedral at Tyre — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> at the firſt ſight to attract the eyes and hearts of the enemies of the Faith:<note place="margin">Cap. 4.</note> as the Panegyriſt at that Dedication doth expreſs it. From thence that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101138:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>(<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) great and heavenly quire made haſt to perform the like ſolemnity at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan. Cap. <hi>43.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Jernſalem!</hi> the City of the great God, he was once well known in thy palaces and in the gates of <hi>Sion:</hi> The glory of all nations the joy of the whole earth, where the Lord ſaid he would dwell for ever! in thee was he worſhipped with the beauty of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs; till by the rebellion of thy people, the wicked obſtinacy of thy Prieſts and Rulers, when they truly murdred the Lord of life and glory, the vail of thy Temple rent in ſunder, the gates flew open on their own accord, and a dreadful voice was heard let us go hence. Then did the Scepter and the Glory depart from <hi>Iſrael,</hi> then was thy holy place prophaned with all impurities and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the duſt. Behold now thy King cometh, whom thou wouldſt not to reign over thee, in greatneſs, Power, and Triumph; over the deſpiſed lodging of his birth, ſhall be built a glorious Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to his Name. Every place, which formerly entertained his Sacred Perſon, ſhall be turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Oratory, every ſpot of earth whereon he ſtood ſhall for ever be accounted holy ground. Here will we raiſe Altars, to the memory of every action which he did, and conſecrate to eternity the particulars of his Sufferings; hither ſhall reſort, from the utmoſt ends of the earth, the wearie Pilgrim, and proſtrate pay the Vows, which he made in trouble, at his ſhrines, here the mournful penitent ſhall power fourth floods of teares where He wept, ſhall love the place where He was ſcourged and by thoſe ſtripes ſhall be healed. Here ſhall the diſconſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late ſpend his life in ſacred retirement, and all devout employments; here laſtly ſhall men dedicate their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101138:11"/>time to Diviner Studies, write Commentaries upon his Life, and defences of his Religion. To this new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> it was they made haſte from <hi>Tyre</hi> to the Encaenia of a Magnificent Temple, where was a concourſe of holy Confeſſors and Biſhops from all parts of the Chriſtian World, attended by an innumerable company of every particular Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Some ſanctified the Solemnity with devout prayers, and pious exhortations; ſome made Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the virtues of the Emperour, extolling the ſincerity of his love to Religion, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour he paid to Martyrs. Others compoſed devout meditations, from paſſages of holy Scripture, to the occaſion. They who were not of ſuch attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments made their Devotions (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) with unbloody Sacrifices,<note place="margin">Ibid. cap. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note> and myſtical Services, praying for the peace of the Church and Happineſs of the Emperour. The frequency of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Dedications are not here to be mentioned, nor need we add any thing in defence of them; it being ſo much a part of natural Religion, and Gods ready acceptance of this in the Text ſo ſolemnly performed, is an infallible Argument, that many Ceremonies in divine Worſhip are approved by him, for which no particular command can be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced. It is childiſh impertinency, when God hath given us ſenſe and reaſon, beſides general rules in Scripture, for our direction, to expect a divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation to lead us by the Hand, and mark out every ſtep we are to go. I have hallowed this Houſe, that thou haſt built, that is, what you offer, I do accept and will bleſs it, for thoſe ends you have deſigned it. But ſome people are ſo afraid of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as if they had been preſent
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101138:11"/>at the Thunder and Lightning, the Shakeings of Mount <hi>Sinai.</hi> So terrified are they, at the very name of the Ceremonial Law, that they are not capable of underſtanding what it is; nor will learn to diſtinguiſh betwixt, what is ſo indeed, and what are truely the reſults of nature and common rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Nazian. Orat. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Of ſo undoubted Antiquity it is in Chriſtianity, that <hi>Blondel</hi> himſelf, (who writ an Apology for his own opinion, rather than St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s) acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges Dedications to have been performed with the Solemnity of Prayer; onely he urges againſt the Superſtitious Ceremonies of the Romaniſts; and will be ſure not to allow the Biſhop the chief diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of the Office, which yet is ever reckoned in the number of his Prerogatives.</p>
            <p>They, who firſt affixing a typical ſignification to every particular under the Law, diſpute that none ought to be retained, as receiving their full imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion under the Goſpel, ſeem not carefully to have attended the conſequence of the Argument; whileſt they endeavour to give it an unbounded force, they make it altogether loſe its ſtrength, encreaſing the ſhadow to ſuch a vaſtneſs, as to take away the light of the very Sun, and bring Univerſal Darkneſs upon all Divine Revelation. If all ſhall be received for the ſence of Scripture, which the Allegorizing wits of men, warmed with thinking, have obtruded; who ſees not, upon what a Rack the litteral ſence will be put, tortured into ſuch confeſſions as will call in queſtion its Truth, and deſtroy its Being. All Ages, as our own, have found, that the immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate indulging Spiritual meanings, have rendered the Scripture but a dead Letter. It ſeems a pleaſant
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101138:12"/>thing to make apt ſimilitudes: Allegories have been the entertainment of great wit, and high Devotion: too oft alſo the refuge of Hereſie, when deſerted of plainer Scripture, We give due reverence to the pious induſtry of thoſe, who by this method of Interpretation, have performed any thing which may with pleaſure perſwade to Vertue, or illuſtrate the Analogy of Faith. Yet will not the quickneſs of Fancy be alwayes found, to ſerve the ends of reaſoning. It may delight, but not convince; it may incline, but not ſatisfie the inquiſitive under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. Such do appear to have been the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagancies of this kind, that having treated Sacred Scripture with the like levity, as the Jewes by their Gematria, they have been little leſs ridiculous, nor can they be entertained without prejudice to the common Faith, and great inconvenience in believing: the Egyptians and Greeks had their Mythology, The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ology moralized: the Jews not without probability, pretend an ancient Cabala they ſay from the time of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſeemes to refer, well underſtanding the learnnig of his own Nation. The Scripture alone muſt put bounds to our Faith in this particular, nor are we obliged to acknowledg any other Types, than what we find there declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. As to our preſent inſtance, the Temple, or Tabernacle is not ſaid by the Apoſtle (Heb. 9.9.) to be a figure, but thoſe Ordinances of worſhip therein obſerved, Gifts and Sacrifices impoſed on them till the time of Reformation.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>John</hi> ſaw no Temple in the new <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> that is, as the Jewes, in the dayes of the Meſſias expect a Temple, but different from any they had before, as is that deſcribed in the viſion of <hi>Ezekiel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:101138:12"/>2. What Dedication doth imply, as the reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nableneſs of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That hereby the place becomes pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick for Gods Service. For the Church of Chriſt being Catholick, and intended to include whole mankind, it is no leſs honourable than neceſſary for the maintenance of Religion, that the celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be as publick as the deſign of it; both the better to invite the unconverted to the ſame Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as alſo to preſerve it ſelf entire from Herefie and Schiſm, which private Conventicles have always bred and fomented. One reaſon of thoſe Hereſies which much defaced the beautie of the primitive Faith, was that they being denyed the publick exerciſe of Religion, were conſtrained to divide in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many little bodies, whereby he who had a mind had the opportunity by his wit and ambition to tyrannize over the Faith of others, and to compoſe a Church of Diſciples peculiar to himſelf. And it was great wiſdom in the Diſpenſation of the Jews, the inſtitution of three general Feſtivalls every year, at which the whole Nation was bound to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, whereby they ſecured the unity and integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Worſhip, whilſt they had no long inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals to forget the conſtant ſetled method of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or to invent and propagate new. They had alſo but one Temple in the whole Land, which as it ſignified the profeſſion of one God, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the plurality of the Heathens; ſo was it alſo an effectual Bar to all Schiſm and Innovation. The Religion of Chriſt indeed is of another Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of much larger extent than from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> intending the advantage of more than a little ſpot of ground, not two hundred miles in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101138:13"/>length; for all Nations ſhall worſhip him, and his Dominion ſhall be from one end of the Earth to the other: And therefore our Saviour told the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Samaria,</hi> that neither in that Mountain, nor yet at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſhould they worſhip the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but whereſoever a Temple was built, there, in the purity of his ſervice, might they find his preſence. Happy was that time, when in what part of the world ſoever a good Chriſtian might chance to be, he might have found the doors of Churches wide open to his Devotion, and God worſhipped in that form and order, to which without either ſcruple of his own Conſcience, or offence to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, he heartily could conform: when ſo incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable were the differences of Worſhip, that ſo prudent and pious a Biſhop as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> thought it his duty, whether at <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Milan,</hi> or any other place, to obſerve its Cuſtoms, and joyn in Sacred Offices: when he might have travelled from <hi>Eaſt</hi> to <hi>Weſt,</hi> and as ſoon have diſcovered another Sun, as another diſtinct allowed Religion. Even in S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s time, if a man askt the way to a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, no <hi>Donatiſt</hi> (that had not the ill humour of a <hi>Jew</hi>) durſt have preſumed to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect him to his own. But now into how many thouſand pieces doth that Catholick Doctrine ſtand divided; whilſt it is forced to put on as many ſhapes, as frail men are ſubject to imaginations? How many Altars ſmoak to it, with no other than the Sacrifice of Fools! Strange Fire, and Incenſe, wherewith God is not delighted, becauſe himſelf did never kindle it: As if the Holy Jeſus had been deſigned ever to remain in Infancy; no where to be found or worſhipped, but in Stables, unſeemly,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101138:13"/>unhallowed places; and his Religion never to take part of that Happineſs which Inſpired Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets have foretold. In Religion, as in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, were our underſtandings placed in clear and pure light, undiſturbed with paſſion, prejudice or intereſt, and Earthly affections, we ſhould ſoon diſcover the eaſineſs and native ſimplicity of its motions, no contrariety, no irregularity there; and that only man made <hi>Epicycles,</hi> little fancies of his own, and falſly ſaid God lodged in them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Dedication doth imply, that we part with our own right in the thing, and make God the ſole Owner. So <hi>Solomon</hi> prayed, Ariſe, O Lord God, into thy reſting place, thou, and the Ark of thy ſtrength: And therefore at the Conſecration, both of the Tabernacle and Temple, God by moſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and extraordinary ſigns declared his taking poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of them: for the Glory of the Lord filled the Tabernacle, and the Cloud filled the Houſe of the Lord. God is the Lord of all the Earth, and all that we have, and by the particular aſſignment of ſome part, we confeſs his Title to the whole. So the great King of <hi>Perſia</hi> (to whom, ſitting Enthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in <hi>Suſa</hi> or <hi>Ecbatane,</hi> the Author of the Book <hi>De Mundo</hi> hath compared God) uſed to demand <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of thoſe Nations whom he intended to bring under his Subjection; and that little he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted as an acknowledgment of his Dominion, as the denial was a bidding Deſiance to his Power. There are two conſequences of this.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, That ſeeing its Gods own, we take great care of our behaviour towards it: Reverence my Sanctuary; Holineſs becometh thy Houſe for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101138:14"/>In our entrance put off thy Shooes (in Weſtern phraſe our Hats) for the place whereon thou ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt is holy ground. Keep thy feet when thou goeſt into the Houſe of God. The Adoration by bowing, is a moſt reaſonable acknowledgment of that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty we do approach: The Greek Liturgies call it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to put us in mind, that we ought to have the humility, as we have the indigencies of a Penitent Sinner. What compoſedneſs of mind, and ſetled devotion, purity of heart, and innocency of hands, ought to be preſerved in that place, where God ſays his Eyes and his Heart ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually? he will more eaſily pardon the miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of life committed amidſt our ſecular im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, than thoſe Errours which profane that place, where Religion ought to be our bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That we never think of alienating it from that holy uſe to which we have deſigned it. So jealous is God in this particular, that he would not ſuffer the Cenſors of the Rebels to be imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to common uſes, but for the ſervice of the Temple. He asks the Queſtion by way of Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Will a man rob God? Sacriledge is a Crime which the Heathens generally ſo abhorred, that in their Hiſtories more ſevere judgments are record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have befallen the Committers of it, than of any other ſin againſt the Law of Nature. The <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> in the height of their Conqueſts, always preſerved due reſpect to ſacred places; and when they thought it convenient utterly to deſtroy a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they always by certain Ceremonies invited the Gods, under whoſe tuition it was, to a fair remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, and civilly promiſed them more fortunate
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101138:14"/>habitations. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a term of the greateſt infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and reproach imaginable. Only Chriſtians (in the Apoſtles words) becauſe they abhor Idols, think God will eaſily diſpence with Sacriledge: Becauſe they have a better name, think they may ſecurely be guilty of more horrid actions. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as God was always tender of his Soveraignty; and, though by methods to us undiſcernable, ſeldom leaves the boldneſs of this ſin unpuniſhed; but firſt or laſt, uſes his own ways and times for the regain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his right, as our own eyes have ſeen. For as by the overflowing of <hi>Nilus,</hi> all particular poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions become undiſtinguiſhed, and would for ever remain confuſed in Mire and Dirt, did not <hi>Geometry,</hi> after the rage of the River is aſſwaged, recover the ancient bounds, and gratefully ſecure that property to which it ows its firſt Original: So when an armed Impiety, in this our Land, as a Mighty Flood, brake down the Banks betwixt things Sacred and Common, ſwallowed up Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches with their Revenues, and laid deſolate the Sanctuaries of Piety and Religion, the Inheritance of the Lord was well nigh loſt in ſo great an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation, had not that God (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) the Great Geometer of the Univerſe, come down with his Line and Meaſuring Rod in his hand, (as once he did to <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s Temple) and meaſuring the height, length, and breadth of our Church, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived every part which it did poſſeſs, and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly reſtored it to all its old proportions.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, We will conſider the effects of this Conſecration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, as to God: I have hallowed this Houſe to put my Name there for ever, and mine eyes and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101138:15"/>my heart ſhall be there perpetually: In all places where I record my Name, there will I come and bleſs thee. By which, and many other expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he aſſures us of his more peculiar preſence in places ſanctified to his Worſhip. I will not now diſcourſe the preſence of Angels in Chriſtian Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies; it ſeeming to Learned men to have Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Scripture, may piouſly be believed, and to be that Retinue which makes up the Court of the Heavenly King. The <hi>Gentiles,</hi> by the Power of Magical Arts, ſuppoſed their Gods impriſoned in their Temples, to inhabit the Images fixed there, and to be refreſhed with the ſmoak and ſumes of Sacrifices. God may be found in Woods or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarts, in a Dungeon or a Priſon, in the wild Fields or open Air, but in his own Houſe is his promiſed reſidence. Here will I dwell, for I have deſired it: Hearken thou to the Supplications of thy People <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they pray towards this place. If a man treſpaſs againſt his Neighbour, and come before thine Altar in this houſe; if thy People <hi>Iſrael</hi> be ſmitten down before the Enemy, — and make ſupplication before thee in this houſe, when Heaven is ſhut up that there be no Rain — if they pray towards this place, then hear thou in Heaven; and when thou heareſt, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The effect upon our ſelves will be greatly to encreaſe Devotion, and promote our Piety in our Addreſſes made in ſo holy a place. There are few, I ſuppoſe, of ſo ſetled a Stoical humour, as to be influenced by no external circumſtances in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The decorouſneſs of the Building, the gravity of the Auditory, the ſolemnity of the Service, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101138:15"/>the ſeparated Relation of the Place, cannot but move a man, whoſe compoſition is ſuch as on purpoſe to receive impreſſions either of pleaſure or diſlike from material Objects. There is indeed a Religion in the World, ſwallowed up in the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel which only ſhould adorn it, where the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Grandeur of Piety tends to Atheiſm; and there is a Religion dark and ſlovenly, as the minds which have made it; containing nothing to invite, but to cauſe to nauſeate and loath the Offering of the Lord. The former winds up to too high a pitch, the latter lets down to too great a laxity; both which do equally ſpoil that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Soul, (as <hi>Philo</hi> calls it) wherein conſiſts the health of its Conſtitution; only the Church of <hi>England,</hi> like Virtue it ſelf, preſerves its Eſſence, by being placed betwixt two oppoſite Vices, its deadly Enemies: Here is comelineſs without aflected gaudineſs, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty without meretricious painting, gravity without a pieviſh moroſity: a Religion, which being moſt fitted to the nature of man, cannot but be moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto God. How dreadful is this place! it is no other but the Houſe of God, and this is the Gate of Heaven. Here are the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Port and Reſidence of that King, whoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings (not like <hi>Iſaacs</hi>) never are exhauſted. Here thou need'ſt not wait for thoſe milder times, when only that Serene <hi>Jupiter</hi> of the Flattering Poet would give a favourable Audience: But when ever thy heart is oppreſſed with grief, or thy condition with neceſſities; when ever thy joys or thy ſorrows, thy Petitions or thy praiſes are become too big for a mortal breaſt, here thou mayſt come and empty thy ſelf, Heaven will receive them. In thoſe Acts
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101138:16"/>of Religion, where we moſt retire our ſelves out of the World, and command our thoughts from purſuance of earthly pleaſures, wherein the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout mind betakes it ſelf to a nearer converſe with God, when the doors of thy Chamber are ſhut, and an awful and reverential Darkneſs fills thy lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Cloſet; when a ſtill ſilence all over gives thee leave to open thy breaſt, and powre out thy heart to thy Father which is in Heaven; when with the fervency of thy Devotion the fire kindles, and thy heart burns within thee; although thou canſt not boaſt with <hi>Loyola,</hi> of being lift up ſome diſtance from the ground, nor tell of dark Viſions of darker Interpretation; yet tell me, if thou canſt, thou hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Soul, what unſpeakable pleaſure thou perceiveſt. Doſt thou not ſee Heaven opened? or rather, do not thoſe unſpotted joys croud in upon thee, ready to overwhelm thee? Although thy Will be Infinite, as is truly ſaid, doth it not here find ſatisfaction? Is not this the Joy which the Apoſtle ſpeaks is full of Glory? Does not the Preſence of God ſeem to forſake its Throne in the Immenſe Heaven, and fill thy little Room, as once it did the Temple? Thou now thinkeſt thy ſelf in Heaven: Thou art much above this World, and in this temper canſt eaſily deſpiſe all its moſt flattering Temptations. The Temple is truly <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Heaven upon Earth;<note place="margin">Joſephus <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiq. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.</note> as <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſays of <hi>Moſes</hi> his Tabernacle, that it was made <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Univerſe; the Holy of Holies was the Heaven of Glory, the Seven Lamps the number of the Planets, placed inclining, to repreſent the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the <hi>Zodiac.</hi> In this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as he calls it, God was; and hither they had reſort in all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101138:16"/>their difficulties: and ſuch an one did <hi>Conſtantine</hi> carry throughout his Wars, that he might never want that Preſence, upon whoſe Bleſſing all his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes did depend.</p>
            <p>In the Viſion which S. <hi>John</hi> ſaw (<hi>Revel.</hi> 4.) there ſeems to be in the ſecond ſenſe, a ſhort reſemblance of the Chriſtian Church: There was a Throne ſet in Heaven, the Metropolitan Seat of S. <hi>James</hi> at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> round about the Throne four and twenty Elders, who having Crowns on their Heads, muſt be the Biſhops of his Province; out of the Throne proceeded Lightnings and Thundrings,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Arrian in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pict, lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> and Voices repreſenting the Diſcipline and Doctrine of the Church; the ſeven Spirits are the Deacons, the number of the firſt Election: Before the Throne was a Sea of Glaſs, like unto Chryſtal, repreſenting the Baptiſm of the Church. And laſtly, their ſet form of Divine Service; they reſt not day nor night, crying, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God Almighty, which was, and is, and is to come.</hi> But more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly we will conſider thoſe three parts, of which eſpecially Chriſtian Temples were compoſed, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>In the little ſpot of ground, through which ye go into the Temple, ſtand and think that more are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried there, than a whole City will contain, Behold the riſing Graves, which ſwell no more with the Great and Proud, than with the Poor and moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed man: No ſweeter Flowers ſpring from the perfumed Bodies of Princes, than the putrified Sores of <hi>Lazarus.</hi> How tame and quiet lye thoſe ambitious Monarchs, and great Oppreſſors, whoſe Voice once, like Thunder, made the Nations trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. See the Rich <hi>Caelius</hi> his Tomb, how are all his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101138:17"/>large Poſſeſſions ſhrunk only to three Ells of ground. Silent now reſt the diſputing Divine, and the wrangling School man: Thy near Relations, and deareſt Friends, whoſe Converſe thou lovedſt as thy Soul, if thou ſpeakeſt will not anſwer, nor tell thee what is the other life. Here the weary are at reſt; no ſighs, no groans, no mirth, no laughter: the Rich taſtes no more the pleaſure of his Luxury, and Abundance; nor do the Miſerable feel the pain of Poverty, and Oppreſſion. Here is no Ambition, no Revenge, <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey</hi>'s Urns may ſtand as cloſe together, as of <hi>Pamphilus</hi> and <hi>Euſebius.</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we all make haſte, and over our Graves, e're long, ſome-body will diſcourſe as now we do.</p>
            <p>Theſe thoughts are common to all mortal men, and were the ſureſt relief the Philoſophical Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens had, whereby they mollified the ſharpeſt miſeries of humane life: But the good Chriſtian hath a more certain Conſolation, being aſſured of a far more glorious Immortality, than they by their moſt ſerious Diſquiſitions could attain: For this is not common but ſacred ground, a repoſitory of Bodies till the laſt day, a Dormitory till the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, proper to thoſe who die in the Faith of Chriſt, and Communion with his Church. And certainly unwiſe are they, who deſpiſing the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Church, pertinaciouſly refuſe to give ſatisfaction to that Cenſure which they have deſerved; and yet think to take as quick a Riſe to Heaven from a Garden, or common Field, as if they lay preſſed with no ſuch heavy burden. Is it a pleaſant Doom to be caſt out of the Church, and not to have the Burial of a Chriſtian, whilſt Saints and Martyrs lye under the Altar? The Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101138:17"/>permitted no Burial to them who had not been initiated into their Myſteries: The <hi>Jews</hi> Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe the Body of him who died without it; and ſome Chriſtians (not condemned for this) Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed others for the Dead: And in all Religions,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Chorus</hi> Ariſtoph apud inferos. Ran. Act. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> none were believed happy in the World to come, who died out of the Communion of their ſacred things. It is good to be wiſe before the Day of Judgment; for Excommunication being included in the Nature of all Societies, without which they cannot ſubſiſt; God, who hath Conſtituted the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of his Church, will not leave its Cenſures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Rebellious without effect.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Porch (or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) was the firſt part of the Temple reſerved for thoſe various ſorts of Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, which the degrees of Crimes, and wary ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Communion of the Church, had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced. They were here kept <hi>ſub ferulâ,</hi> not to advance, but through all the ſeverities of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Diſcipline: Here ſtood the (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menters, who underwent the hardeſt burden of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. Theſe clad in the vileſt habit, Sackcloth and Aſhes, their faces filled with horrour and amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, did implore the prayers of the Faithful en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into the Church. <hi>Proſtrati in medium, antè viduas, antè Presbyteros, omnium lachrymas ſuaden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, omnium veſtigia lambentes, omnium genua deti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentes.</hi> Here you might have ſeen miſerable Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles of thoſe ſins, and that contempt of the Church, which our days have made but the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Mirth and Laughter: You might have ſeen the Politick but unfortunate <hi>Ecebolius,</hi> rolling him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the dirt, kiſſing the feet of the Saints, beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them to trample him under their feet, if ſo to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101138:18"/>die, might ſatisfie for his Apoſtacies. More than this, you might have ſeen the Great <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of the World, with the Retinue of a Prince, but the Humility and Importunity of a diſtreſſed Man, begging of that Reſolute Prelate of <hi>Milan</hi> admiſſion into the Church; which he never, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſatisfaction, could obtain. The conſideration of theſe, and the other degrees of Penitents, (too long here to mention) may make us reflect, how hard a thing it was, in thoſe better times, to obtain pardon of a wilful ſin by the neceſſary Abſolution of the Church; and by thoſe ſeverities, ſhe preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Honour to Religion, reſpect to her ſelf, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by violence, ſaved the Souls of many ſuch, whoſe Salvation we have now cauſe to fear, unleſs the way to Heaven be much broader than it was. In this part, after-Ages placed the Holy La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Regeneration, wherein we were made the Sons of God, and Heirs of Eternal Life, being by the Anſwer of a good Conſcience enlightned, and born again: Which Efficacy not only the <hi>Jews</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to their Baptiſm, but the Heathens alſo to their Initiations, that they only after death ſhould be happy who were ſo Initiated, and miſerable who died without it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From hence, through the great and Silver Gates, they entred into the (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) Body of the Church, in the very middle of which ſtood the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Pulpit, whence the Congregation recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved inſtructions of Salvation from the Mouth of the Preacher. This, the Object of equal both love and hatred, is not more deſpiſed by ſome, than by others held in admiration; to theſe a Stumbling Block, to them 'tis Fooliſhneſs; both dangerouſly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101138:18"/>perverting its Original Inſtitution. Of ſo great and ſerious conſequence is the well management of it for the Churches Peace and ſafety of Religion, that whatſoever Craſty <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> ſhall gain this <hi>Palla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> into his poſſeſſion, 'twill not be long before he Storm the City, and with Fire and Flames deſtroy the moſt flouriſhing Kingdom.</p>
            <p>From this Throne the Tetrarchs of time (as a Great Wit calls the Clergy) command Obedience, about one quarter of the year, from the attentions of their oft too heedleſs Auditories. This is the Watch-Towre, whence, as from an Egyptian <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros,</hi> the Seers of God diſpence unto the World the Everlaſting Goſpel, a Lanthorn to their feet, and a Light unto their paths. Hence they cry aloud to tell <hi>Judah</hi> his tranſgreſſions, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> his ſins; and give warning of thoſe Shelves and Sands which have drowned multitudes of Souls. From this place it was, S. <hi>Peter</hi> at one Sermon converted three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand to the Chriſtian Faith; and ever ſince, Pious Biſhops and Doctors of the Church, have daily ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all well diſpoſed minds. Here ſtood <hi>Origen,</hi> in whom all the Science both of the Ethnick and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Philoſophy was united: The ſtream of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence, as proſound as was his Learning, clear as his Speculations; no Mud or Froth, but what was raiſed by his too near approach to thoſe Rocks, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which unwary Wit too often ſuffers Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack. Hence <hi>Nazianzen</hi> declaimed his Chriſtian Philippicks; and hence <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> by the Might of his Courage, and Zeal of his Elocution, ſtopt the Sun, as it were, that it did not ſet upon the World, delivered Orthodox Faith from a moſt ſtrong Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, and fear of ſudden death. Here laſtly ſtood
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:101138:19"/>the Great Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the very Top of Eccleſiaſtical Eloquence, who by his Pious Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, and Power of his Oratory, drew the minds, and bended the hearts of his Princely Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory: No Vice ſo high, which his Rhetorick would not reach; none ſo ſtrong, which his Preaching did not make relent: And how fooliſh ſoever to preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and prophaneneſs Preaching may appear, yet managed by ſtudy and wiſdom, it oft-times breaks the hardeſt heart, makes the moſt ſeared Conſcience feel; it will ſtartle the moſt ſecure ſinner, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time or other will be remembred by thoſe who moſt deride it; a dark night, a ſick bed, or an uneaſie ſleep, will reconcile the man to this Heavenly Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and make him abhor the thoughts of jollity and indiſcretion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, Through the Gates called <hi>Beautiful,</hi> they aſcended to the (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) the Holy Altar, from which I have too long detained you. To this Holy Table therefore let us go, and participate the Food of Souls: There let us offer up not only this Oratory, but our Souls and Bodies to his moſt Faithful Service; promiſing him never more, by any wilful ſin, to prophane his Temples, nor drive away his Holy Preſence.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:101138:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
